all right so just so you know this is
rolling but just to kind of get make
sure that we're not peeking and I just
got this thing so it has like peaks and
valleys no anything
I don't either so we're in good company
okay but it's just gonna it's just going
to record the conversation fine um and
this is the Becca that's a Christian
that's the print of that she's for the
cover of the village life the ladies
book okay Tran there yeah so that's
really something that's really okay well
that's know was from when he was
fourteen isn't it wonderful
yeah when is it from no one knows it's
from a little bitty print store in New
Haven yeah and it didn't have a date and
it didn't have a signature mm-hmm
I have no idea it arrived in that it
looks like paper to me yeah but I I
don't know but it was nice not to have
to ask an artist or an artist estate for
permission yeah yeah in my house okay
but sorry okay yeah whenever I mean you
could finish up taking you
I don't mind so whatever the two of you
yeah I mean she was just gonna go to a
coffee shop go through the usual listen
to I mean
I mean it's whatever makes you leave
while you - oh no no no yeah just do
whatever you done just yeah and then
I'll give you a ring when we're not
finished okay so I know you're you know
you don't use a great amount of digital
devices as well you use one zero
well the iPad does that's very new
that's that's this last year okay
oh I I got it in a strange way and I
learned how to use it very very very
very slowly okay I've only been able to
use it for oh I don't even think a whole
year okay so yeah
so I all just so then in some ways this
might be really short movie but I'll ask
kind of is this a bad basically focused
on the use of digital equipment it is a
sort of that's what that's Mike that's
kind of my slant
I mean that's kind of like the way I got
money probably but it's but it's become
much more interest I've become more
interested in just sort of talking to
the artists and writers about the ways
that their processes have evolved and
how it's changed and so in some ways
that that's definitely doesn't it
doesn't matter device whatever you're
using it's just I just AM interested on
how that how your physical day-to-day
works and so while what these first
group of questions are really based on
digital stuff so just tell me to skip it
if he doesn't make sense to you but then
we'll talk more about sort of the
general arc of the career in some and
how those processes change and go back
and forth and so if you would state your
name and the location we're at for this
interview Louise Glick I think like is
spelt with you
and I know love and the names Hungarian
and we're in Cambridge Massachusetts
in my apartment okay and of course I
know the answers to many of these
questions but so what genre do you work
in poetry and I have written some essays
some forwards to books when I was
judging my first book price contests but
in me apologize yeah are you gonna
collect those essays yeah good good
those are so excellent because I you
worked really hard at them I don't work
I worked so hard and they ruined ten
summers I guess a lady's frantic with
anxiety the idea of trying to do serve a
new talent and to describe its
uniqueness
great great and you know it's a natural
offshoot of teaching which I've loved
for years and I I loved everything about
judging those contests and I loved
working with the poet's on their
manuscripts mm-hmm and in the early days
before you know press was convinced that
this was worthwhile I used to buy a
plane ticket for people so they could
come here and spend three days working
okay and then we would you know I would
make very detailed recommendations which
they were free to not take because the
book you're on on the other hand they
weren't free to change the books any
which way yeah because I could say this
is not the book I chose so they had they
they could stay exactly
we were or they could respond to
suggestions and mm-hm and work further
and many of them actually felt a great
need for that kind of work and they just
didn't have somebody who was willing to
take that kind of detailed yeah early
interest why I mean from what I'm
experiencing it doesn't seem to be a
very common thing for is the selector to
make a real interest after they choose
and then they're done and they get their
money in they're on their way I think
that's sort of how most of them feel and
yes that them also don't want this off
the point that you're no no no it's all
it's all one thing most of them don't
want to read a lot of books or some some
time in some contests they're not
permitted yeah they're sent ten
finalists right screened by you know it
varies yeah but if these manuscripts are
being screened by people whose aesthetic
judgment do you question you don't know
what you're getting Yeah right I asked
to see as many as possible and with the
understanding that nothing would be
thrown out and tell where it was chosen
because if I didn't find a winner and a
hundred manuscript so I'm just going to
see the next hundred great and that was
all that was all fun because you didn't
have to read each book here to
completion and you didn't have to write
a little paragraph evaluating it the way
you do for other kinds of things yeah
yeah if you didn't love it it was
unlikely you would choose it you know
put it in the unlikely pile right in my
living room was filled with piles you
know identifiable by me yeah and then at
the end I would
read through the piles to see whether
something got primo promoted or demoted
and mm-hmm
some years were thrilling I mean it was
too much stuff and in those years most
of the runners-up ended up winning some
other well later yeah prize oh okay
this island you would encourage them to
result yeah yeah some people would
submit like three or four times yeah oh
that's that's interesting I don't I want
to know who it is yeah that's all okay
the so what part what time of year were
usually doing that evaluation it worked
out very well because for a lot of that
time I was just working halftime mm-hm
and yell night in the spring semester
and I'll get the manuscripts in December
right after the semester ended mm-hmm
and sometimes it was a little bit of I I
tried to give myself a couple of weeks
of blank yeah and then the cartons would
start to come from the people who were
screaming and yell aloud the
appropriation of a mechanism that I had
picked up from Michael Collier when I
judged the bailiffs price that he was it
revised he had each poet who was judging
shoes younger poets to scream so I chose
ten poets and they got paid it pittance
boots when each of them were at a
hundred books in seventy 10 okay
and kept 90 yeah and that meant that I
had someone to talk to about each of
these manuscripts yeah and sometimes we
would talk before they even said things
and
say read me a few poems and say what do
you want to see this
yeah and I'm on the fence yeah and um I
had great people screaming for me and
they were people whose judgments I
trusted and who sent me very broadly
diverse manuscripts and one thing that I
wanted was a series in which the books
weren't a whole like yeah I not yeah
anyway so no they're different that was
great and then it what it meant that all
the prose writing I did for ten years
was writing forwards
mm-hmm and that's all I have a stack and
yeah I had a few other essays it doesn't
make as pleasing a collection as the
first one yeah but I can't stand the
idea that it's just don't know where no
I I will be very excited to have that oh
not three words not three words that's
not like proofs and theories oh this and
that
oh um no I don't either I want if I
think of okay is it coming out of this
FSG years yeah but not in another
no yeah I mean when I you've got this
next book yeah okay um well that was the
first question but uh I guess the other
I saw I went to a WPS year which was
terrifying I've never been yeah you
should never go but there was a there
was a panel with Richard Steichen oh
right and who were the other two
article and article ins and losing it
daddy to knows exactly and they were
talking I just I caught that second half
but I'd so I heard second talking about
this he's working with you on crash
which was really funny
he's funny I didn't know how funny he
was I didn't know you know I mean like
the book is pretty intense but okay oh
yeah oh really
I like that thank you yeah that's he
made these envelopes cuz he thought he
was gonna be living in Europe hmm and
then you know the message was the
envelope I didn't I don't know how you
can frame them because yeah I don't
they're very nice I think wonderful yeah
and he has another book coming out too
which I saw a long time ago I mean the
other Peter Peter strike us has a new
and oh it's wonderful
is it I really love his first book I
yeah and I I just think he's an
amazement mom and Jay Cutler has a new
book that he's peddling oh so those
first three I worked with really Luther
off really strong book closely on the
first books and with Peter and Jay I
worked a lot on the second two with
Richard much less he it's funny because
he needed a lot of editing his poems
were way too long yeah the stanzas were
too long the lines were too long but you
had to preserve that sense of an
avalanche sense that had long sense and
so it was very hard to figure out but
once he once he saw over a way of
approaching the language to edit it and
still give it mhm
still preserve his character he was he
was an excellent editor and he may feel
that he just knows how to do it yeah
humming sound yeah well I mean we talked
on the phone then yeah but I and I saw
early versions of a lot of poems yeah
well it crush has become sort of its own
mold oh yeah it really has it's been cut
it's it's interesting I mean I remember
I first heard about it at bread-loaf
that year I was there and somebody was
like have you read crush no spec oh like
I'm sorry nearly lost and then I taught
it and then I still have you know what
we know the MFA students kind of at
Idaho and there's some of them were
teaching it or like the guy I wanted my
the guy was actually working for me and
digital is they faced his final poem and
this beeps us off those lines and those
and that sort of stanza style so well a
lot of it is both sound like him you can
see they read the broken
yeah yeah that's the things your heart I
know but uh yeah
are you okay yeah yeah okay yeah then
you can tell me how ridiculous this
interview is later so your primary genre
and so your primary genre is poetry
correct yes so what kinds of devices do
you own or have access also or just you
what what kinds of devices do you have
access to or use for writing I have
access to an iPad I'd never written
anything on it except a terse email okay
and I can't bear reading poems in that
form and in fact today there was a
conversation with my publisher because
they finally figured out a way to their
satisfaction to convert their poetry
listings to ebooks mm-hmm and question
was do that what
my permission and I cannot bear reading
palms in that form
I mean scrolling down the page you have
no idea how long the thing is yeah you
don't know whether you're in the middle
or at the end and Miranda who was my you
know daily editor not my big guy yet
okay I who was the student of mine at
Yale no it's very funny oh I have all
these students down positions up I have
to take to say authority but I turned to
them for you know solace and advice all
the time right Miranda is quite great
and her judgment is wonderful and she
was a wonderful beginning writer too um
anyway she she said she thought it was a
good idea she said for people who are
used to reading in this form you know
it's not such a violation mm-hmm it
makes me uneasy so so if friends for
example when I was in Stanford and
friends would send me drafts of poems us
do yeah I do through the mail right or
at Stanford I would give something to a
secretary but you know there wasn't a
lot that's further up the pike I just
have to go to someone who can print it
you have to have it on paper yeah
and that's well I have to be able to
move my pen around and make notes first
of all yeah and I have to see what it
looks like what if what the duration is
what and I have to be able to read the
beginning in the end I have to have them
all in my head but mainly is that I
don't know how to make notes otherwise
so I have but I have this that gives me
fantastic pleasure in other ways I mean
I love it and it said an endless
amusement and I keep it very near my bed
or on my bed and if I wake in the middle
of the night I turn on the light and I
see if anybody's reading - I always have
that experience around the clock rate
except that I you know I I check it
every four minutes and I'm so
heartbroken when there's no change
same old email from Amazon or you know
even some some website that I patronized
once right and I have a regular
old-fashioned cell phone I only
about five years ago because I'm taxi
dependent I needed to be on the street
and calling the guy yeah so it doesn't
do it doesn't receive emails or so you
need please just and it's a regular iPad
just like a the first no or a larger one
or a smaller yeah okay okay
oh the stream yeah yeah yeah okay that's
the regular size they have the minis now
that's the only kind of different what
happened was
some of this has to be off the record
okay this event I was invited to just
think the golden plate award for
sponsored by held by something called
the Academy of achievement I mean it
sounds so spurious and ridiculous but
but to show you showed up and you got
ten thousand dollars and it was in
Washington DC and the hotel wasn't
honnestly swine no I mean super Swank so
I I asked my agent to find out what was
the fewest number of days I could go and
still collect the food and it was one so
I scaled it way back yeah that I found
that when I arrived that the dinner the
night before for the honorees had been
in the chambers of the Supreme Court
with the justices just just that just
the justices and the honorees yeah I
couldn't you could have eaten dinner
oh no so anyway when I arrived part of
my welcome package was this thing
and it was all programmed with the
winners okay and their BIOS yeah
and of the entertainment of the last
night when we all got our plates
you actually got gold plates yeah I mean
the room was it was a very very good for
banquet me oh yeah extraordinary in this
space I mean if you square it off this
room and then he's off the whole thing
it certainly wasn't bigger yeah there
might have been a little smaller when I
saw the picture an intimate space I
always want people to guess but it's
ridiculous what are they gonna guess it
was like seeing Mozart it was a wreath
of Franklin oh my gosh really
retha yeah she was there right where the
tulips are bow yeah different color so
that the whole thing was eerie
anyway the guy gave you gave me this one
I arrived I said don't give me this I'm
never gonna use it get rid of someone
who can make use of it great he said I
have to give it to you and I said but I
I won't use it I don't want it I'll
leave it in the hotel room please give
it to someone else
mm-hmm and he said I have to give it to
you and he thrust it at me and then I
was holding it then I seemed to have it
so I took it to the hotel room and I'd
seen that people push the screen so I
pushed the screen yeah nothing happened
I mean it wasn't connected to anything
but and I thought well I apparently
don't have the gift so I I then brought
it home well actually I had somebody
ship it to me uh-huh and then I kept
looking at it and thinking I guess now
that I own this I should learn how to
use it but I I lingered in that state
for about six months and then at some
point I asked one of my former students
from Billings Indiana like yeah don't
touch with the Yale students sometimes
come up here to work on their stuff
mm-hmm and one did and I said what do I
have to do to learn how to use this yeah
and he said well you need to get Wi-Fi
and I said how do I do that
do I call a TM table I called Comcast he
said call Comcast so I called Comcast
and they asked me questions I couldn't
answer yeah do you have a blank do you
blank blank and I said I know nothing
you have to just assume I have nothing
yeah but he I I thought this is not
gonna work it wasn't working so I called
the student back and I said write me a
script here's the kinds of thing
I was asked ya tell me what I say right
so I went back and I recited in my
script and someone came to the house and
installed a device mm-hmm and no one had
told me they had these little strobe
flickers and I'm epileptic right so I
thought oh this is never gonna do yeah
so I called the student again and he
said you can turn it around turn it some
strobe is facing another direction yeah
and I did and but then I still didn't
have an email account so then someone
else came up to work on poems and I got
an email then I was so horrified at this
transformation that I couldn't do
anything for it there for another six
months and then Robert Pinsky I told him
I had an email and he sent me a photo of
one of his grandchildren ah and I opened
this little thing and there was a photo
yeah and I got Wow and so I learned
certain skills
I still can't add an attachment uh-huh
no that's not what they're called
and oh okay yeah so somebody has to do
that when I need to know yeah yeah like
I wanted a HBO because I couldn't get
you to go yeah but then I have all of
these you know names passwords and I can
never remember what they are then they
asked me you know you said you want to
change your password yes and they asked
me my special secret question which
makes absolutely no sense what is your
favorite pet's name and I didn't have
pets I mean except when I was a child so
I yeah and they say well we can't change
the question because the the person who
this is
came up with this question and I think
you know that I never would have great
rady I still haven't figured that out
but now I try to write down the put a
password so you have some other place to
get it from in my phone book oh okay
because I think there's such a long list
in my head and I don't know which one is
for which great great so all that stuff
I hate yeah
no it's it's it's a it's such a daily
part of life now and we just we all
dislike it and when it's new to someone
it's also well kind of realize how awful
some of it is I like the adventure of
the nail and I
watching I've watched a lot of
television and when what I was I had
bronchitis this winter and so wonderful
because there it was in bed with me I
didn't have to go anywhere
yeah I didn't have to sit in a chair had
it all right there and you had endless
stuff to write you Netflix or oh you
know okay you're set yeah yeah I own
something I own em mmm you thought I
didn't want to wait for the lesson yeah
it's worth it those are pretty intense
and once dust ident this the real spine
thank you yeah I loved it I loved that
show I did too
and we just finished that one oh yeah
not too long ago yeah yeah the what else
have you liked TV wives um whatever what
are we watching now the Americans is
very good is it good yeah that's a very
good one have you seen Friday Night
Lights I've watched some of Friday Night
Lights machine you've never seen it
right now so we need to do the whole
thing yeah I did it several years ago
yeah I love that so I watch that at
Stanford this year and I thought it was
gonna take me there five seasons I
thought this is gonna last me the whole
my Stanford experience it's gonna be
great mm-hmm and I finished in about two
weeks but I didn't want to watch
anything else it's yeah
a marvelous book and there was something
about I mean I can record and watch
things on demand but yeah there was
something about the fact that I could do
this anywhere mm-hmm and if I went to a
hotel I could do it I still have it you
still do it you would you know it was
just I it was it was an amazing
discovery for me and I loved that show
and I ended up watching the last season
a second time and then I still didn't
want to watch anything else so I watched
the first season think I was ready
um but I have not have not found a new
thing since then since then well if you
watch the wire okay
I watched the wire on TV at Frank's
house ah yeah dopey unless he has
equipment uh-huh yes yeah like quality
equipment um well I'll think of some
some other ones
I'm sure oh yeah we should talk about
I'll definitely let you know because we
watch a lot of okay all right moving
along no that's good I mean like you
know it's about being a person
so you're you kind of that's I gotta
kind of adjust on the fly here but I
think I'll just skip these because you
don't really you know you don't write
any poems on the iPad you never have
them in digital format until they go to
your publisher essentially and then
though how do you know how they do it
you send them a type script because then
I have to prove the digital and be sure
there haven't been mistakes
yeah always huge mistake hmm I could pay
somebody to do it but it would still be
same problem same happy yeah prove it
yeah um I imagine that I'm stuck with
that for life because I cannot imagine
typing poems on that so when you you say
that F is G and then someone types like
or do they scan it and then I mean do
you know how they do it
no okay cuz I mean there are ways they
should be what I can tell you know if
you wanna ask yeah um do you want em hmm
maybe I don't know I I'm just I mean
it's just sort of in inin but you then
once they do that then they send it back
to you and you make sure that
everything's right and then I mean you
go back and forth with them with the
proofs for quite a bit right I remember
when I was a student I think you had
would have been beaten OVA you were
working on her for seven ages and you
were telling me how you were reading it
backwards no so yeah how much that
what's the thing you do horrible yeah
that's great because you can't you it's
in your book and you you hear it pretty
you know you you remember your palms are
fairly memorized almost all of them so
like once and especially when you're
working in the book like when you're
going back through you're hearing it you
you're I make substitutions so unless
you unless you read it out of order
yeah you're gonna be doing that yeah
yeah um okay well it so that was the
first section but there's not much to it
because it's mostly digital but then
this is more practice and so I've kind
of delineated the writing process into
kind of a three-step sort of things so
there's the composition there's the
there's the revision and then there's
the sort of organizational archival
point and that's just my kind of
construction for this interview if that
doesn't make sense to you we could talk
about in different ways so and I have I
have kind of like the beginning
questions which is kind of to give us an
art like a idea about the arc of your
career but and this question I'm sure
you'll love but how long have you been
writing professionally would you say
well I was trying to write for
additionally I've been writing since I
was a child and I had a very high
opinion that my early work so I was
sending books out to publishers in my
early teens oh really Wow but I did have
I did have that intense dream and I
developed it as as anybody has to a very
tough skin I mean I have enormous vanity
you know every time one was rejected
didn't matter that I was 15 years old I
thought I'm never gonna write better
than this this is this is the climax of
my vision and no one wants that yeah
that was how hard but I continued to
send things out and when I had when I
started working on what became my first
book I was in my late teens and from the
time I was I think 23
this was published I think when I was 25
something like that
I had I think 28 rejections okay a real
law but I had some poems in magazines
mm-hmm but it was all of that was in
place by the time I was probably 12 that
sort of ambition and drive yeah yeah and
then there were long periods of not
writing at all that were harrowing
continue to be have mm-hmm and I had
different mechanisms for trying to get
through them the greatest discovery was
teaching because I finally learned after
the first really lengthy this is
completely off the track of what you
want no it's absolutely no no the my
next question was described the arc of
your career so this night well the first
time that that happened I went I
firstborn had been published and I had
not only did it happen I've pretty much
done what I what was in me to do mm-hmm
I had also formed evolved the style in
which there were no complete sentences
they were just little bullet-like
fragments and every time I thought to
write I couldn't I couldn't no longer I
can't make this in so it's gonna be
grammatical but
could no longer it was it struck me
write a sentence so I realized there was
something about that bad particular wall
that I had hit that had to do with
syntax and I thought I have I have to
write poems like no sonnet on his
blindness that are all ones
or as close to that as I can manage yeah
and I couldn't do it I couldn't do
anything that approached it and I
couldn't at the same time write
fragments anymore and the more I
couldn't write the more I repudiated the
world I thought that the problem was
that I was too worldly too involved in
the world too diverse in my interest so
I became more and more hermetic man
dedicated and I would sit at this was
living in Provincetown for part of this
time in New York City and I would sit in
Provincetown at a very beautiful desk
that was made for me by my photographer
boyfriend with all of these marvelous
objects to gaze at and I heart
horrifying and you know on a good day I
would write an article but had a really
good day there would be a noun you know
tree but you know we never moved yeah I
couldn't get beyond that and I thought
I'm not I have not consecrated myself
sufficiently there needs to be more for
swearing and I fine I had I had a bed of
nails kind of life just sitting in the
sort of soup of my failure for a year
and during that time I had one or two
teaching job offers in those years it
was very much easier because you the
economy was different and you know there
weren't all these MFA programs
especially if you were female I had a
book out and I don't know that I would
have gotten a tenure track job given my
spotty education but I I could certainly
I had these offers hmm and I kept saying
no no no no because poets shouldn't
teach I mean there was that long long
list of things poets shit'll do yeah I
should never have children they
shouldn't teach they shouldn't go out in
the world they can eat but finally I was
invited to do a colloquium in Vermont
and I hated Provincetown but I I didn't
I didn't know how I didn't want to just
begin moving and to sort of pin the tail
on the map kind of way I was making my
living as a secretary I could have done
that anywhere in that period hmm but I
thought I'll just stay here until the
future presents itself so I went to do
this colloquium partly because John
Barrowman was there he was a hero of
mine and I
to be able to pay tribute to him I
wanted to say you are great artist
mm-hmm and I salute you which I did get
to say but he thought I was just you
know a chick on the make it was really I
didn't know how to say to him you don't
understand I've never said these words
yeah
in any case I realized about the minute
I got to Vermont I thought I'm supposed
to live here I just instantly love the
place and it was a four-day thing and
there were all these you know English
teachers at Goddard College hippy
institution with a naked dorm
Amina's like that and they said you
should come here and teach and I thought
why not I'm not the poet I have to face
this disastrous fact mm-hmm and make a
life so I say yes and of course they
weren't doing parent offer me a job
they were just drunk and English
teachers writing to me great but by then
I had had a sort of Epiphany and we I
corresponded with two of those people
who are my still oldest
dearest friends Ellen Voight and prose
writer Katherine Davis mm-hmm and by the
three days before the semester started
there there was a job cobbled together
for me for one semester and I moved to
Vermont and I got a room in a rooming
house with a bathroom down the hall
and the minute I started teaching I
started writing again and I still feel
about teaching that is a kind of it's
the most miraculous thing I ever
discovered because I can't always write
and a lot of periods go by and I don't
write but I can always teach and I will
always need people who fascinate me
who are doing things with lines that go
places my mind has never gone and I
won't find that stuff in books by dead
people and contemporaries yeah new
sounding stuff and it changes me and
electrifies me and to work on the
material that's still malleable it was
it was the experience of working on my
own stuff
but I didn't feel competitive I didn't
feel a lot I was so strange because I am
very competitive
yeah but not with my students and I
wanted those poems to be as great as
they could be or in my view mm-hmm
and so that's what that's still that's
served me very well and especially once
I discovered undergraduates because I
couldn't know them for four years and I
loved and Williams was Williams was
Nirvana you know I do not there and I
thought I've never been around such
smart people yeah I was terrified but I
also was thrilled and you know that a
lot of those years were years when I
couldn't do anything but then some of
them were years when I was writing a
blue streak and teaching and it was
never
oh I teach one semester and then I write
or I teach and I write in between
classes no I mean if I was writing I
would write when I taught and then and
in fact after the experience in
Provincetown at this
desk I I have a horror of the special
place yeah the you know secluded cabin
the writers retreat I just can't bear
them I I want to be and I want to be
without tools I often have no pencil and
no paper so I have to borrow them or or
buy them but I don't want to presume
anything I just died there's going to be
a line coming into my head that would be
great yeah and when I'm working on
something then it so so the shape has
always been periods are in the desert
you know without a language yeah some
and then work which was set in after I
was 50 there were most of my books
written very fast like six eight weeks
heywhat which book did that start with
the wild life to others and after that I
thought I can do anything I can fly
planes and I remember my husband saying
you are going to really hit the wall
very soon yeah and he was right
I develop neurological symptoms the
whole Wyatts
I have not slept the whole of that
summer practically hmm and one side of
my face started twitching and I had to
teach that fall and I remember sitting
in class like this so that nobody would
see that my face was long and the
neurologist said I don't think this is
anything you mean it'll probably go away
in a couple of months which it did but
every so often I think something like
that could come back again you know just
some some we I mean it was it's weird to
write that fast and you don't have a
sense of agency very hard to revise
because yeah you can't picture you you
don't have you don't remember writing it
you just were sitting there and then it
was and the the last two books village
life and then they were slower what
there were they were standing so this
especially village life the newer one
there were lots of moments when I
thought this is never going to be a book
I don't know how to put this material
together mm-hmm
so I mean if you think back when you
before you hit this sort of stride where
you were reducing books very quickly I
mean what what was it like say writing
have some marshals or long okay it took
many years I I revised poems heavily and
constantly one poem I remember took two
years to write for my mother mm-hmm the
opening lines it was better when we work
together in one body I had those lines
in my head for a really long time and at
the beginning at the beginning I felt
very grateful because I thought o-22
really beautiful lines this is going to
be a poem and I'm screaming this is
exciting I have at least these lines to
cling to and then time went by and
nothing happened no other language
attached to that little shard and so
that those those phrases that language
became a torment was the first thing out
here in the morning murmured in my head
the last thing I would hear at night but
it was it was a chastisement a torment
you you don't know what I'm for
right and I tried to convince myself it
was a high coat you know thought well
maybe it's just a very austere
abbreviated mm-hmm but I didn't think
that and nobody I showed it to thought
that either so that took really a very
very very very long time to write and
had lots of different approaches and
ended up being a kind of collage of
pieces of language from different old
poems and during that time you weren't
where you just were working on the one
poem I was for a long time yeah and so
there weren't other poems coming in and
out of this it's just and that is that
traditionally how you work or there is
one poem and then the next moment then
when we finished it yeah yeah and then
sometimes I sometimes there'll be a
massive revision you know oh you know
what one addition to an accumulating
manuscript makes it clear how the things
should be ordered and
see you can make a lot of short little
changes and the other stuff because of
this new thing but so some of the books
are slower some are the earlier books
were revised much more the lighter books
less mm-hmm those though they were there
were revisions and all of them and
though most of them proceeded at some
point rapidly from I would say over a no
on that were there were hiatuses like
the Verona was written into fast periods
and the aged one October because I mean
that was such a good chat book and yeah
okay yeah and I had October and I had
prism great and I thought these people
these two poems can't be in the same
book I mean they're just complete
opposites and then there were two years
when I wrote nothing hmm and I keep it I
haven't attended to this
years but from many decades I kept this
chart of what I wrote when and each year
would be written at the top of it
no the years were like that and the
months were like that mm-hmm
and if I wrote a poem then I would write
its name and if I wrote nothing I would
write an X and so I would when I got
depressed I would take this thing out
and I would see all these lines of X's
and then they would be at the end that
would be a little gust and a little gust
would be completely different from what
had preceded the X's yeah so I began to
be I mean I trust a little strong but I
just figured this is how I it goes
through me and there's a period usually
now after I finished something of being
happy as I go I don't have to write yeah
I feel kind of on vacation and I have a
sense of secret pleasure has no one
seeing it and no one's has anything to
say about it
mm-hmm but I loved it and
and it's finished and I like last year
was such a happy year for that reason
yeah you just play back they made me
take my I think this beautiful Atlantic
trunks and all with salad on paws of
pussy-willow uh-huh
I remember that yeah myself still for
grounded in my brain anyway so so kill
the rest of those poems in the Brno were
written after this two year gap mm-hmm
and very fast really fast and none of it
figured out I mean I didn't have
Persephone I didn't have didn't have to
serve I'm hurt me everything
yeah I've been reading a lot of Henning
Mankell and I was trying to put
an image from each of his novels and one
of my poems oh okay
is he is he a mystery writer yeah okay
Swedish Swedish I was
I hate travel but I was is this the near
wolf book Nero Wolfe mirror okay okay
no that's reps doubt that was from much
longer ago no Michael is living okay
Swedish married to one of a more
Bergman's daughters well yeah and I
think he's a genius I love those books I
think he's a great brother stylist I
would recommend them start with one step
behind though don't start at the
beginning because the first book is not
good and you wouldn't read the rest okay
but very dreary compelling
[Music]
it's there's there's his detective plugs
ahead and he you know he notices small
things that don't make sense and turns
them over in his mind but he's not a
firebrand
he's not handsome man and there's a kind
of dreary sameness to his days but the
book the books are fantastic and what
they what they they're notion of what
triumph is mm-hmm
triumph is persistence and then it turns
into comprehension you know a pattern is
revealed yeah it's what they're really
I'd love them so I was reading those and
I think something of his prose style
crept into my poems
hmm I don't know that another person
would think that but in in Averno or I
mean you never know did it transfer
through into a village what life at all
no that was book yeah so if we started
so so you had your first sort of period
of silence after first born and until
you started teaching at Goddard and then
was it was it like that sort of like a
repetition every time I mean if you
finished a book didn't you
I mean you had the pleasure but then you
also had the silence or did some
someone's jumpsuit was yeah yeah with
with marshland there were a lot of
silences in Darien took about seven
years okay I mean first one was
published and
1968 but it was finished in 66 hmm and
how son Marchand was 75 so it didn't I
was put in touch with Dan helper and who
was starting echo by Stanley Kunitz
family said this this young sport loves
your work and I thought you know I don't
want to have to send this out 28 times
yeah and so I thought I just felt with
someone family recommends who loves it
mm-hmm so it was published pretty soon
after it was done so that was a very
very long boo period but I feel as
though firstborn is just an artifact
from another life and that really by
writing life began with the house on
marshland
and I think you know I can see how each
book came out of its predecessor mm-hmm
after that what do you what do you mean
by that can you see like the dew point
poems in the previous book that were
harbingers of the next or you just or
sort of terms of language I know you
also I mean you speak in your interviews
about how you go through and try to kind
of eliminate the language of the one
book before you yeah but even in that
sense so that you certain stylistic
takes you you try to recognize and
prohibit the way I tried to prohibit
fragments but they seem like the work of
the same person not some sort of journey
and I try to make them as different as
possible what and what is the I mean I'm
interested in what the work of doing
that is I mean is it you've just lived
with these poems so often that you
recognize immediately what the stylistic
tics are and that they're easy to do or
is it something that when you read
through the book and it's finished
formula oh I see that and I see that and
these are the things that I need to
really work about eliminating I never
see it when I'm working on the book yeah
which would be probably suffocating yeah
yeah so it's only afterward I think well
I can't do that again and and then
someone's you see isn't things like
isn't it odd I've never used a
contraction ever and then you think well
I guess I have to figure out how to use
a contraction and that becomes a whole
with what you realize is that that's
quotidian speech that was what I hadn't
used I mean so then you look in order to
use contractions and questions you the
Delphic voice evaporates and the human
is introduced in its place and that was
a hard moment because a lot of people
who admire my work admire that for
exactly the thing that was now no longer
present and when when what what period
was this um between which I felt
achilles okay so coming into triumph
achilles that was that that was the one
of the ticks that you were burnt that
was one of the changes that was being
made yeah right and then so go triumph
Achilles to the next one
Ararat and then Meadowlands and then
wild iris no other way wild iris
Meadowlands oh wow I was in okay you're
pretty car I'm pretty close
I've been reading The Collected and I'm
just it's so interesting to kind of like
move through time as you're moving
through yeah what did you feel about
that I mean by publishing The Collected
Poems oh it it's surprised to me yes I
always thought it was a terrible idea
well first of all it's not the collected
and I didn't think of it as that but
it's fifty years of writing and yeah and
I was initially appalled and then amazed
at its size because I thought it would
be about 300 pages long and that when
Miranda said it was six and initially
688 said no one will buy this we have to
squeeze it it has to get a little er
yeah I thought I thought it was a
valedictory gesture I thought it was
suicidal to do most of my life I I was I
was repelled by it in principle the idea
of doing it myself was horrifying mm-hmm
and I I had begun to feel I mean I never
read my old books you think I mean what
I don't have no reason to but at some
point I had to do something from from a
bunch of books or I had to do reading
and I and I was asked
dude yeah so I was reading through the
books and I I didn't hate them I mean
often once I know you finishing your
euphoric and then pretty - pretty soon
you feel a sense of humiliation and
shame you're just yes think about what
you've just done so then after that you
don't go back and you know then you're
trying to prove you can right mm-hmm by
writing something else or you know the
book gets horrible reviews and you had
this feeling nothing I'll show you the
people's pants poke yeah but I I was
reading these old books I'm thinking
they and I like them and I was proud
that I wrote them and I remember a
couple of years ago but I sometimes do
tarot readings with Dane 11
Oh Dana's sister is a professional
clairvoyant and Dane is very good with
cards I trust her greatly and so we were
doing one I I guess I had done the cards
with Dana
but then Dana's sister Karen the
clairvoyant was visiting her so we had a
three-way conversation on my breath
they for birthday present about the
reading and Karen asked me questions
sort of the way a shrink does you know
leading questions she said you know what
is what have you you've been thinking
about it a nice writing and somehow it
came up then I I was very frightened by
this pleasure that I was taking in my
old work because I feared it meant I
would do no new work hmm
and Karen said I think you have to
embrace that I think that's she can use
words like path but you know that's
yours that's what you have to do you
like this you can't pretend that you're
not feeling it you just must follow that
feeling and see where it leads
so where it led was to a readiness to
see these books all put together which
had been proposed earlier in fact I was
contractually obliged to do it but I
would never have been press and there
was always the problem of the fact that
echo owned most of the books and Dan
helped her and resented for a very long
time possibly still continuing this
moment my switching publishers which I
did simply because his interest seemed
to be elsewhere so I I missed though I
missed the attention mm-hmm
in which book was that I mean did you
ever knowwwww ever know and it was the
very inflamed parting and for a long
time he would
relinquish any of the books to young so
none of that was possible but it was
fine because I didn't want it yeah
and then somehow or other that was all
negotiated and I did want it and I found
it invigorating and generally a very
pleasant thing and it made me feel I
didn't have to I didn't have to do a big
square thing anymore I could and
anything that I did was gravy and it and
I really like this new book it's not
like anything else I'm not done
it's sort of surreal it's got prose
poems in it mm-hmm
that's gonna be a shocker I think I
don't think people are gonna like it or
understand it like I I think of it as
very kind of light-hearted or it kind of
be the kind of well there's a lightness
in it a kind of casual shrugging bravado
like that I like it's not beautiful kind
of like like certainly though you're the
right yes
but a lot of people think it's
terrifying because you know a lot of it
is it
at the end of time but it's not written
as a struggle mm-hmm and it's not
written as capitulation it's written as
what do you know here we are yeah sort
of like that underneath a there's tones
in it that are not unlike when you do
don't know that kind of scratching your
head thing but but I kind of Mary Mary
bleakness yeah it's always a pleasurable
place to be yeah anyway so um did you
find in actually writing those poems
that there was a different way like
physically you were going after them or
anything else I mean it was it well the
last couple of books I've written a lot
of it longhand which was a great
surprise because everything up until
Averno was written on a typewriter I
love the composition including first
born no first formless by hand first
Remus Mahan and and everything from
marsh land caliber no it was composed on
a typewriter okay and it's one of the
reasons that my papers are not valuable
because people there's not everyone sort
of you know they'll be pages with little
scribbles but usually I just put in a
new piece so somebody who goes through
all of these typewritten drafts unless
they the person happens to know my work
intimately mm-hmm no they don't you know
it just looks like a lot of tight poems
you know authors hand a parent but
that wasn't well I don't know why I I
started keeping a journal when I had
whiplash and like someone said you
should start writing about what what it
feels like because you'll discover that
you're not in as much pain as you think
you are I started this notebook
recording my whiplash symptoms and the
agony that they entailed and so I it was
one of them I know stood in bed at night
reviewing my day and it became the most
crucial piece of my day and I'm
listening to the telephone weather
forecast which became village life no I
figured that out it took a long time but
so I would I would I would listen to the
weather forecast and when I would read
dial and listen to it again and there
was this wonderful voice that would say
good evening Boston and you would
realize that the same thing was going to
happen to everybody
you weren't just selected specially to
be rained on you know it was everyone
was going to have rain and it was the
first time I actually understood that
everything was going to everyone was
gonna have something you know I mean all
those times I stood in the drug aisles
of the supermarket thinking Louise they
can't have made all these products just
for you it must there must be a mark
someone else is buying these things and
then I would think yeah they're buying
them but they they only use half whereas
I need ten and anyway so but
whether it did make that knowledge
present and we while I was writing my
whiplash symptoms that's I would get in
a very Spacey place and so I started
making those four poems hmm and I would
so as not to interfere confuse things I
I did the poems in the back of the book
moving toward the middle mm-hmm and the
journal of my paint journal from the
front and I started you know yeah and
after the whiplash went away surprised
there were many other things to complain
about it really life so this week this
this sort of diary of grief complained
misery fear chronic anxiety occasional
nice things reported but mainly it was
the book was sacred to that mm-hmm and
it was a real it was a real source of
sweetness in my life I even when I
didn't have a bad day or I didn't have
any real pain or that wasn't sick I felt
that I owed it to the book - yes a the
worst so there would always be that yeah
and then there would be these notes and
so I have a whole bunch of these eerie
notebooks and then I I realized that
we're working kind of well and I liked
once I started working on a poem and I
would work on it the way I always had
mm-hmm only a lot of it was longhand
look at and the lines were getting
different shaped and and the advantage
of that was I could also do it when I
was commuting you know I had a car
service in those years and Averno was
the first thing I did when I was at Yale
mm-hmm
and I remember working on the poems in
the car and then I would transcribe that
into the notebook in the back mm-hmm and
at a certain point each one would have
to be there'd be enough material so I
had to play that on the typewriter and
see how it looked in type and one fact
of working on a typewriter that's either
I don't know whether it's an advantage
or not I imagined for pros it would be
my pros Reuter friends all love the
computer yet when I get to an impasse or
an awkward line I start have to start
over so it's a new sheet of paper and
you have to do the whole thing again and
so problems emerge in those retyping is
like your your fingers will hesitate
over something you thought was resolved
and you realize it's not resolved you
realize you have to do something
different mm-hmm
so you had those you were you were kind
of making those revisions in in the
actual transcription work so yeah I mean
to you yeah just from some sort of
almost like a almost like a like a
practiced feel of the yeah your hands
wouldn't type it yes
realize something was wrong either the
line was wrong in
was lineatus which would be simpler to
resolve more the whole trajectory of the
palm was awry yeah that was and then
you'd have to go back and do more we're
going to at that point would you do more
work in the notebook before you went
back to the typewriter or once you think
then I started working on that then what
would happen would be I'd have these
typewriter sheets and I would start
working 200 in the same timeframe mmm
okay you're back and forth yeah and then
how do these just cancel the weather
report by the way no those are the I'm
the presence of that absolutely yeah
where's the bathroom I have to go feed
the meter
oh okay great um do you have a visitor
pass we part put the car yeah you just
parked right here and then we can give
it back there yeah as long as it's in
the permit parking yeah yeah just put it
on
[Music]
[Applause]
were there any other things like the
like the weather report for any other
books I mean did that ever happen before
were there any sort of other I mean I
know other books had like something
where like a ritual to which you were
responding in some sense
well wild iris was a garden yeah I had
been reading garden catalogs for tree up
two years of writing nothing yeah all I
had where it was garden catalogs and
plus I'd seen when I first moved to
Vermont to clarify and who told me I
would write five books and I've written
five that was the fifth oh and I thought
that's it and I thought it's obvious
because there's no beauty in Ararat it's
just the whole weird gift is dribbling
away and then
I read garden catalogs and listening to
the Don Giovanni for two years and I
thought I'm brain dead you know of
course I can't right yeah and and then
that that came in a burst yeah no it was
um it was summer Oh summer okay I
started walking around the garden which
had been the only thing that I did yeah
and um and things were coming out of the
ground and I thought I might try and
write something about yeah flower so in
terms of like so the difference then I
mean now we kind of have an idea of the
handwriting to the typewriter and
whatnot I mean what was it like when you
were just type writing your poems I mean
you would you you'd sit down at your
desk or wherever I mean the typewriters
are kind of really things you'd have to
be in one place wherever you were you
know they would always be it would be
episodic okay um and didn't have to be
my typewriter for example I remember
when I was working on what was it seven
ages Vita Nova mm-hmm I remember writing
some of those poems on an airplane I
wrote two on one transcontinental flight
and then I got to a vine and I had to
borrow a typewriter but that was
possible yeah and then I had to work it
out tie
so there were things that were but I was
at that particular point I was really on
a roll I mean I knew who's from
everything was turning into a Paula yeah
so I felt I could be anywhere and I
could write with anything and I could
write with you know food colouring
charcoal and I could I could make
actually very crude like powerpoints and
I would know how to assemble a oh that's
fine so when you're in that sort of
stage where are these are they just
coming to you are they coming from
overheard statements or is it it's all
just there and you're just kind of
waiting to release it I
it's nothing overheard it's some weird
brain corner that totally you have
access to and it exists it's like a
temporary shelter exists for a very
short time and it's not like you think I
could go back there you just think yeah
do you see any patterns now that you've
had these experiences happen to get him
again that that sort of anticipate your
getting to where that brain corner opens
up or is it's no I am I'm always curious
so he's mysterious and the last two
books have been a little slower in what
I felt was a a good way because the
stamina called for and that other kind
of composition is so extreme plus you
don't get that you don't get a very
prolonged experience of immersion you
know you get a very intense fast hit
yeah but I really liked the feeling that
I had
it was like writing a novel that I
hadn't put in in village life I had this
sound to go to that was like a place and
it was accessible I could get there it
wasn't like this special trick pony you
know it was yeah and it would it meant
that the composition was a year and
stunt which still seems pretty fast yes
but it's not as fast as six weeks yeah
absolutely that was we didn't know that
that was the best six weeks who's the
fastest how long was about iris uh more
like nine weeks but there were three
poems that were written the year before
they just were crap but once I wrote the
wild iris I once I wrote the bulk of
that book I knew where the the crappy
poems didn't seem so crappy okay and one
of them did you know it was a blanks and
David and Meredith's daughter mm-hmm did
you know David and Meredith at all no
take a classics class well she's my
godchild and she was at that point very
little and this was the period in which
I was writing nothing and I I said
Elizabeth give me the title give me a
title or a first line and I thought I if
Elizabeth asked me to write a poem I'll
have to do
yeah and she did and I it got used what
was like red rose on a lowly vine it
didn't get called that finely but you
know it was a little song like Valentine
of a poem yeah but but then I mean if it
if it looks do you like that's your
that's your output for two years okay
dad
yeah but you know I had a place in that
book yeah so that was so in the name
while iris was the first book I wrote
fast but it had had these three weeka
SHhhh poems that can absorb into it
mm-hmm so I don't know I don't know if
what will happen now I imagine all the
sand into some of this
and you know this is just a question you
know how much more you get to do you're
fine I'm still feeling surprisingly
happy with my last one and I know that
until I hate it
nothing's gonna happen how long have you
been finished with it it'll be a year in
September so it's still a baby how do
you know I mean you you have a kind of
really final sense of finality for these
things and then I guess like I'm
interested in how you do you have like
just like a physical sensation when that
happens or is it your brain stops moving
in that direction and it's so you can
sometimes have that but it isn't
finished okay
I mean that's happened to me a number of
times they're usually always means that
there's something that isn't written yet
hmm
even though you just cannot imagine what
it is and the meadowlands was like that
I just I thought
but it was clear I might be good at
putting books together and I can figure
out what each body of work seems to need
and there was no way to put that
together and someone was missing and I
thought it was probably some more
sonorous column but it wasn't that it
was Telemachus was missing oh okay and I
wrote those poems in I think 10 days and
maybe from and then it's a breeze
you know I'll think about you know King
you know into place I think that's I
like I've just been eyeing that book too
yeah that's very funny
that's very funny I know I think it's a
I think it's a screen yeah but um and I
like that I mean I like I like tunnel
variety yeah a lot and I like it and
what I read but I think sometimes this
you know the last two books I drove
people crazy with village life because I
had maybe 400 different orders and they
were all not right um yeah that would be
that I could see that book being
difficult to put together I knew how I
knew where I wanted to start anew where
I want and even in between and I think
it was on that or two of something
happening to divide it how did you learn
how did I mean did you learn how to put
together books like this I mean like
what was the what was the sort of
education your own your education in
that sense each book learned from the
material and I think I've learned from
students - okay I I think that that I'm
a very good editor yeah and I was felt
it
I had stuff on a page I would have some
good instincts about I mean if there was
anything to be gotten out of that
material I would find it mm-hmm
so a sort of sense of being able to put
to use the most pathetic limited samples
of language but if you just give me some
words doesn't matter how bad they are I
can do something yeah I felt the same
about manuscripts I thought if there's
if there's a way to put it together I'll
find it
mm-hmm my own books and other people's
books too
I mean in the way I'm I mean I'm sure i
drive some people crazy because I just
look at their manuscripts and I say no
he's leaving all to me you're doing this
terribly and I was that kind of a mother
you know they say don't feed yourself
really you know just don't know how to
do it
the Gees you said I'll feed you you know
and I people people don't like that and
it's also possible that that that one
could be wrong or or that there could be
something something I missed
mm-hmm but I think it was it was always
it was a think something that you learn
when you write very slowly so you don't
have a huge outpouring you know the
small amount then you have to make
though as far as you can hmm and so you
learn how
to move the parts of a poem around you
move you learn you learn how to be an
editor out of a sense of lack yeah
and from that gross capacity to organize
disparate things into something that has
a sense of dramatic shape it is that
that sort of a sense of dramatic shape
is that your intention for most of your
collection even I want the books to seem
like that but it's not as though when
I'm working on them I know what it is
yeah I pretty much don't when do you get
that sense well I'm starting to put it
when you're starting to see them all
together and you start seeing these
weird overlaps and resonances and echoes
that you hadn't planned yeah I mean
proofing this my new book I I see these
strangest parallels and language
language recurrences that I mean you
could say yes you have a limited
vocabulary these words that you use yes
you still remember them but it's also
then it's like dreams you know the mind
is is somehow the mind is making an
organization that is beyond what what
be comprehending or apprehending
faculties take in initially when you're
when you're working the living so when
you're working just on an individual
poem when you're revising it what's
what's like the mode there and you're
going back are you just deleting are you
substituting or is their primary or just
whatever you whatever the palm needs
you're having service to it yeah yeah
aim I mean nothing's more if I can tell
myself that a poem can't be made with
just the leading things that's great
yeah that's two for the price of one you
get the deleted lines if they're any
good to you somewhere else yeah and you
get a poem but oftentimes you can't just
delete often so sometimes you can take
out everything that's weak and
transitions that are obvious but what
you then rekt is the feeling of duration
the poem has become too brisk mmm and
needs to have a feeling of moral
languorous unfolding so then that's a
problem because you don't know whether
you're supposed to and and the place is
where you had
before or were they the wrong places was
that part of the problem but each poem
is its own little task you just you know
for a long time it's a it's a problem
you haven't solved and then it becomes
something that you have solved yeah and
is it the same thing I mean is it the
same feeling of finality that you have
with the collection that you have with
an individual poem I mean that there's
if there's nothing more to be done sort
of yeah well but also that it gives you
pleasure yeah you like the shape that it
makes yeah and you like it better than
you've gotten ever could you know so all
these poems you just thought were so
cumbersome and there was no way that
they could be organized that we just
didn't see it yeah suddenly you actually
like them again well has that has your
mode of revision has that changed it all
over the course or has it been fairly
consistent I'm sure it's quite different
yeah but I yeah I mean the poems are so
different that
there must be that the approach is
different right
I mean now I'm much more like
approximation I like a sense in in the
poem of not the sort of Holland perfect
formal you know the epigrammatic mm-hmm
I want more the kind of that kind of the
kind of speech okay
the sense of casting about for a phrase
I like that feeling mm-hmm
human sounding ruminative rather than
exalted but you know I think of a ver
Noah's the books always seems to me I've
said this a million times this is
probably on there already so maybe these
books seem vertical and some of them
seem horizontal hmm
usually they alternate so they'll be a
kind of odd to despair or book followed
by panoramic book but the last two both
seem to me kind of spreading
though they're very different you know
each other how many people are you gonna
do this with ten Jesus you'll be out of
your mind
I know it's okay let's see I guess
you're number seven eight oh you've done
a lot yeah yeah I've done quite a few
does everyone out there Frank
yes it's very interesting what people
want to talk about and people who I've
done people who know me who don't know
me and so there's some wariness and then
there's some sometimes there's not and
sometimes people who know me are wary of
the questions more and this you I mean
honestly the questions haven't really
but I mean you've answered them without
my asking them so that's that's been
that's good it's a good sign no no yeah
I think there's I think there's plenty
the I didn't like so when you're
revising are you reading them out loud
to yourself this isn't is this is that
something as part of your practice I
know for some of the other writers
husband I I keep I keep trying to make
this point in poetry readings I I hear
with my eyes I I mean the experience of
reading a poem for me with my own eyes
mm-hmm contains an aural experience yeah
and when I hear it I feel angry and I
feel that there's an obstacle between me
and the it of the poem the obstacle is
the reader who is determining and
deploying emphasis and also the form
which is turning a kind of web-like
experience into a narrative everything
goes by once yeah and I I hear and the
argument made is yes but then you can't
hear it but I don't hear it when it's
read to me yeah and I don't mutter it to
myself
I hear it in my head though and I hum it
in my head hmm I mean I can hear you can
hear like almost like musical notes or
tones - I can hear rhythmic structures I
remember with meadowlands I had this
sense of the book it was the only time I
had this I had a whole I felt I had the
whole book in my head I just didn't have
a single word yeah but what I had was
really make Ultem alternations I
shapes that were clustered and dense and
more open shapes and it was almost as
though there were there was a musical
line and I would hear the you know
rising and falling I would hear Karl
parts and I I felt even tried to
annotate it in some way so that I could
follow it but it was like a hum yeah it
was like someone was one I heard
somebody say I think they're of some
kind not a poet something about the way
a child learns speech lying in its
cradle and hearing the shapes of this
the shapes made by it by the speechless
surrounds it and it doesn't understand
words yet but it understands and for me
poems have been like that I mean I
remember reading when I was really
really young reading not baby poems but
great poems Jim Spears songs and I had
I'm sure no idea what was being told of
her none but I felt like I thought I was
getting something out of those poems I
could hear I could hear the fear no more
in the heat of the Sun I could hear the
grandeur of that
that the rhythm I mean somebody could
turn it into an active scanning the line
but it it that makes it so kind of
plotting yeah but you do
I did hear things yeah that way but with
my eyes I mean my eyes make I turn what
I see not into all my argument or a
reasoned thing yeah a lot of that stuff
I miss what is the poem saying I often
don't I have no idea but I know how it
sounds
yeah that's its own sort of yeah
intelligent communication to or any
means yeah that's it no that's that's
really fascinating well I'm sure there
must be a lot of people who write who
have this feel that they're yeah no I
think the own sound comes to them
visually well it's like I'm in some
sense these it right I mean it yeah it's
close to that sort of description but
it's not that quite really yeah but it's
an interesting correlation um
due to people I know you you work with
with fellow poets on your poems correct
I mean you're sending stuff to to you
certain readers etc do you work on
individual poems of individual times or
is it usually in a collection everything
I write goes out goes out okay and how
does I want someone to look at it yeah
preferably right away yeah how who are
those people where they have them in the
same people for a long time or they just
changed from a change I mean is um
certain periods certain people mm-hmm
sometimes you'll feel somebody is the
book you feel is really these poems if
they're ever gonna be understood by
anyone
we'll be understood by X yeah and you're
usually right and then you get when when
X says this won't do you trust it
because the person is basically on the
side of the work
yeah whereas if you show it to somebody
who from the outset says it's just a
disaster it's not gonna be if the book
is classic a you know it's too late to
unwrite it we're gonna get written and
you could then suppress it if you wanted
but yeah so it's it's shifted I mean
there's certain people who have been
constant for a very long time Kathy
Davis mm-hmm
she has been stratospherically helpful
and and I like working on her novels and
I learn a lot from working on prose what
do you I mean what have you learned
or do you learn you learn moving around
much bigger pieces
I mean Kathy's folks it's not so much a
question of that but there have been
books where I felt there's too many
characters and such and such these two
could be translated and other times I
think I felt things were in the wrong
order or that too much time was spent on
the particular thing but with my former
husband who was a quite terrific prose
writer it was often the question of
really moving around blocks of prose hmm
the way you would do in a poem
you'd move a line in a poem but in prose
you would move a paragraph
and I thought so I learned it's like
weight training like that goodness I
could move bigger masses and it was very
useful you know I don't think I would
have written Ararat without that and I
think if I hadn't written Ararat I
wouldn't I would stalled out as uh yeah
certain kind of lyric poet right well uh
I have some questions about why you
chose not to write a computer to use a
computer
I never electic and I I didn't like I
learned that I didn't like looking and
it's a screen yeah the early computers a
lot of it was said it was not good for
epileptics okay and so you just and then
I didn't like I did I didn't like it I
like to paper I've got pages
I like type I love typewriters what do
you love about typewriters it's a big
question
I don't know I
is it a sound thing is it a female thing
no and I actually since the period of
burning my hand like I doubt I don't
type anywhere near as well because I
don't have perfect feeling in that
finger mm-hmm but it was the sense of
how sort of slovenly handwriting became
form mm-hmm I don't get that on this I
don't see lines on the screen call you
the same way and I don't feel as though
I'm making the letter well I do well
often I'm not I'm making the wrong
letter mm-hmm I I don't know why I like
it but it's probably I don't know why I
like it but it's been it's been such a
consistent part yeah every book yeah you
to skip all these computer questions and
yeah I mean you you correspond with many
people yeah how I used to be a much
better letter writer has that changed
quite a bit like I mean with receiving
in your mean you're sending out with the
kind of computer rise or has that is it
just sort of yeah it has changed a
little
yeah well but I long before I had my
little red friend I I had stopped
writing letters the way I once did I
mean it was a period in my life when
even like
ten 12 years ago I just wrote lots of
letters to lots of people and I loved
getting letters back and I loves writing
letters and then that stopped I don't
know why it stopped yeah but it wasn't
because of that what I've noticed with
this is I have now correspondence with
my first husband whom I had we had
exchange we would exchange letters every
two years or something they have very
informal letters yeah and and there was
a period in which he needed someone to
confide in
it was far away and so we had a a little
period of much more intense exchange
very short and I saw him and that his
current wife I saw him for the first
time in 38 years last summer
oh and we like each other and I thought
his life was just great
and it's helpful to kind of substitute
for a phone call and you don't feel like
making a phone call
yeah and it gives people a chance that
they would have with a letter but not a
phone call to respond when they're ready
to and not have a moment forced upon
them in which they have to react yeah so
so I I have very happy thoughts about
this which just has nothing to do with
with writing yeah and then I think you
know it was a big
when I switched from a long hand to the
typewriter maybe it would be equally
transforming - mm-hmm switch to a
computer but not an iPad yeah I would
need a big board and yeah but I can't
use a mouse still hmm I can't the ice
when I see that little it makes me very
skittish and upset yeah
so yeah you'd have to be maybe a
touchscreen but I think we're I think
what we're ended so thank you so much
please have we ended the car well
[Music]